Hello everyone and welcome back
to English Pod, my name is Marco.
And my name is Katherine
and today we have a
great elementary level
lesson all about having
fun.
That's right, today we are going to have a
lot of fun and well before we explain what
exactly we're going to do, why don't
we take a look at vocabulary preview?
Very cablery preview.
Okay, so the word we're previewing
today is a noun, it's a thing.
It's a roller coaster.
All right, a roller coaster, so that's what
we're going to do today, we're going to get
on a roller coaster, but
what is a roller coaster?
Well, a roller coaster is
something that we see
oftentimes in parks,
amusement parks, and it's
like a little train, but
it can go upside down
and it goes very fast and it turns and it's
supposed to make you scared and happy.
Okay, so it goes very
fast and yeah, many
people have probably
seen it, it goes very fast
and as you say up
and down, and well, you
just get on it because
it's fun, you go fast
and you get scared
because you're going so
fast and sometimes
you're going upside down.
Exactly, and for some
reason, I don't know
why, but in many romance languages,
the name is Russian mountains.
Exactly, yeah, it's also in Spanish,
it's also a Russian mountain.
Yeah.
So, I think the reason is because back in
the day, back, you know, 100 years ago when
you were starting, the first
roller coasters came from Russia.
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
So, that's why it's public.
Well, that's a theory, I'm not sure, but
take a listen to today's dialogue, we'll
hear it one time and
when we come back, we'll
be talking about more
interesting and exciting
phrases and words about roller coasters.
I'm so excited, we're
finally here, Six Flags
Magic Mountain, this is the
best amusement park in the world.
All right, settle down now, you're
going to give yourself a haul to tack.
I can't believe they charge us $35 each,
seems like such a rip off, don't you think?
It's not like I'm going
to get on these things.
Whoa.
Viper, that's the world's
highest and fastest roller coaster.
You go at more than 100 miles per hour.
I'm going to go on that
one, can my mom please?
Can I?
Chris, I'm not sure you should
get on that, it seems a bit
too much for you and we've
just had breakfast 30 minutes ago.
I don't think it's a good idea.
Come on, mom, I can
handle it, I promise I
won't ask for anything
else besides it's not
like I'm going to throw up or
anything, let them go, he'll be fine.
Alright, yeah, this is amazing,
see how I ever got it, look.
All right, we're back.
Wow, interesting,
I think this is very
common, you get on one of these things,
you go so fast that you just throw up.
Have you ever thrown up
on a roller coaster, no, never.
No, no, we need it.
All right, well maybe it's not that common,
but let's take a look at some of the words
that we hear in this conversation
between a boy and his parents.
Alright, so as we
mentioned, this word throw
up to throw up, why
don't we take a look at
that one first, although
it's almost at the
end of the dialogue,
what is it to throw up?
To throw is different than
to throw up, so remember
that these two words go
together to mean, to vomit.
That means that the things in
your stomach come out your mouth.
So like we heard in
the dialogue, they came
in like, "Well, yeah, it's a
very disgusting sound, right?
"
And so sometimes people throw up when they
eat too much, sometimes they throw up when
they're sick and sometimes
they throw up after
riding a roller coaster and so
this is an important phrase to know.
Or like when you're on
a boat, you get seasick
and you throw up or in a
car, sometimes you get carsick.
All right, so as we mentioned,
we're also visiting an amusement park.
So why don't we explain this
word a little bit, amusement park?
Okay, first of all,
everyone probably knows
the word park, you
know, it's a public place,
but in this case an amusement park
is a park of fun, amusement means fun.
And so it's usually a
place that you go to
and you pay a price
and they give you a ticket
and you can play all day long, so they
have roller coasters and food and shows.
So probably the most famous
or well-known amusement
park is Disneyland, so
that's an amusement park.
Exactly, and there's lots of fun
things to do for people of all ages.
All right, and now the
kid was so excited that
the mom said, "All right, you're
gonna give yourself a heart attack."
Okay, well, a heart
attack is another serious
health issue we talked
about throwing up
before like is when
your heart stops beating.
Right.
Okay.
So maybe something is stuck or
there's some problem with your
heart and there's no more
blood going through your heart.
And so it's a very,
very serious issue, but
in this case, she's
saying, "You're so excited
you might hurt your heart,
you're gonna have a heart attack.
" You might hurt yourself
because you're so excited.
Right, so she's
exaggerating, that's not really
going to happen, but
she's trying to warn him.
All right.
Another mention that
they paid $35 for each of
their tickets, and he
thought it was a rip-off.
Okay, rip-off is a
great, great phrase that
we use in spoken English
to describe something
that's unfair, so a
price that's unfair.
Okay, so you can
maybe go to the market,
right, and you ask how much a
sweater is, and they'll tell you it's $100.
You think that's a rip-off?
What a rip-off.
I can buy a sweater for $20, so
a hundred is definitely a rip-off.
All right, so that's a rip-off.
It was a rip-off.
He's not very happy with
how much money he paid.
Not at all.
All right, and now the
kid was talking about the
rollercoaster that is
the highest and fastest
rollercoaster, and
he said that the speed
was at more than 100 miles per
hour, so what about this miles per hour?
Okay, this is very
important if you go to
America, you'll see that
the speeds on the road
are all in miles per hour,
so mile is a distance.
And per hour means
how many miles you can
travel every hour, so in one
hour you can go a hundred miles.
So we have the equivalent, right,
we have like kilometers per hour.
Exactly, and so miles per hour, kilometers
per hour, these are both called speeds.
Okay, and well this
is called the imperial
system, right, you use
miles, you use inches
in feet, whereas the
kilometers or centimeters
or meters you would use
the metric system, right?
Exactly, because the
counting is done by
meters, meters metric,
so in this case we're in
America, we know that
because the speed limit
is a hundred miles, or the speed
here is a hundred miles an hour, miles.
We know that we're in
America, because the speed
the boy is talking
about is miles per hour.
Very good.
But in North America, and
that's pretty much it, right?
I think they use miles in Britain.
Really?
Yeah, I'm not positive.
I'd have to check with my British friends.
All right.
Okay, so that's all the words
we have for language takeaway.
Let's listen to the dialogue again, and
we'll be back to explain some phrases.
I'm so excited!
We're finally here!
Six Flags Magic Mountain.
This is the best amusement
park in the world!
All right, settle down now.
You're going to give
yourself a heart attack.
I can't believe they charge us $35 each.
It seems like such a
ripoff, don't you think?
It's not like I'm going
to get on these things.
Whoa.
Viper.
That's the world's highest
and fastest roller coaster.
You go at more than 100 miles per hour.
I'm going to go on that one.
Can I mom please?
Can I?
Chris, I'm not sure you should get on that.
It seems a bit too much for you, and
we've just had breakfast 30 minutes go.
I don't think it's a good idea.
Aw, come on, mom.
I can handle it.
I promise I won't
ask for anything else
besides it's not like I'm
going to throw up or anything.
Let them go, Carol.
He'll be fine.
All right!
Yeah, this is amazing!
See how high up we're going?
Whoa.
All right, we're back,
so now why don't we
start with three phrases that we have
prepared for you today in fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
Okay, this first phrase, Marco,
is definitely a parent phrase.
Okay, so this is something that you
often hear parents sing to their children.
They say, settle down now.
Settle down now.
Teachers say this too.
Yeah.
All right, everyone, settle down.
That means if I'm really
excited and I want to talk and I'm
running around the room and
my teacher says, settle down now.
That means quiet down, go
slowly, sit down, don't talk.
It means calm down.
Calm down.
Yeah.
So to calm down, to relax.
Exactly.
All right, and now the next phrase
is a very kid's phrase, I think, right?
That you would use on your parents.
So if they say, no, you can't
go to your friend's house.
Oh, come on, please.
Oh, come on, come on.
All right, so what do you
mean with that phrase?
Come on, come on, what?
So in this, we have a child
who's asking something.
He's saying, can you
please let me do something,
please, come on, that
means I'm encouraging
you to change your mind
or to let me do something.
So please let me have my way.
Right, right.
All right, so come on,
and you don't only use
it as a child or with
your parents, right?
You can encourage
your friends to like, come
on, come with me to
the bar, come on, let's go.
Come on, you want to, and
our last phrase, I can handle it.
Okay, this is next to the phrase, come on.
So the boy is trying to explain
that he's big enough and old
enough to go on a roller coaster,
but his mother doesn't know.
She says, oh, I don't
know, you're too young.
And so he says, I can handle it.
That means I am big
enough and old enough to
go on a roller coaster,
I won't have a problem.
So you can do it, right?
Basically, I am good enough to do it.
So for example, if I
give you a very hard
project, you can say, I
can handle it, I can do it.
You could also say, I'm very
busy right now, I can't handle it.
Okay, I can't, I can't do it, I'm sorry.
I can't do it.
All right, very good,
interesting phrases
there, they're very useful
and very, very common
in spoken English in North
American, well, a lot of places.
So why don't we listen to the dialogue
for the third time and we'll be back.
I'm so excited, we're
finally here, six flags
magic mountain, this is the
best amusement park in the world.
All right, settle down now, you're
going to give yourself a host attack.
I can't believe they charged us $35 each,
seems like such a rip off, don't you think?
It's not like I'm going
to get on these things.
Whoa, fliper, that's the world's
highest and fastest roller coaster.
You go out more than
100 miles per hour, I'm
going to go on that
one, can my mom please?
Can I?
Chris, I'm not sure you should get on that,
it seems a bit too much for you and we just
had breakfast 30 minutes go,
I don't think it's a good idea.
Come on mom, I can
handle it, I promise I
won't ask for anything
else besides it's not
like I'm going to throw up or
anything, let them go, he'll be fine.
All right, yeah, this
is amazing, see how I
ever go, whoa, all
right, all right, so this
amusement park magic mountain, it actually
exists in the United States, right?
It does, and six
flags is really a brand,
so there are many
different parks, amusement
parks called six flags
and each one has a
different name, I'm not
sure where magic mountain
is, but that one's in
California, yeah, then
you have like six
flags greater America,
yeah, that's my Chicago,
that's a little bit of
Chicago, yeah, so they're
basically amusement
parks and they're
famous because they have
really great or intense
roller coasters, right?
Exactly, so the one
that we heard about in
today's dialogue is
called Viper, like the snake,
and that one is at the,
the amusement park
in California, you
mentioned, but the famous
ride in Chicago is Batman the ride, because
you sit on a seat, but there's no place for
your feet, so your feet swing in the wind,
and it's very fast and you don't actually
sit on a train, right, the track is on top
of your head, exactly, so you're hanging.
So you see everyone
downstairs, well, not
downstairs, down at the
bottom, and I hear they
have a very serious problem
with people losing their shoes.
I heard about this,
people wearing sandals and
they just fly out
exactly, so I want to warn
everyone, if you go to
Chicago, you go to these
upside down, these
flipped roller coasters,
you should bring real
shoes, not sandals, well,
as we mentioned, it's
a, in many languages
in the romance languages,
they're called Russian
mountains, so I wonder,
for our Russian listeners,
you have any intense
or great roller coasters
in Russia, I mean, if
they come from Russia,
they should have amazing
roller coasters there, right?
That's right, or do you
have any idea why we
call them Russian mountains
in other languages?
Please let us know, our
website is EnglishPod.
com, we also welcome your
questions and comments
and other issues, so until
next time everyone, bye, bye.